So, a few more questions
that are kind of suitable for reflection
um
came up and I thought maybe we can just
like address and go through like um
practical like how to practically
think about and reflect on certain
topics that can really be the
the basis for the right type of
meditation instead of you know the
the common um
self-hypnotic attitudes and outcomes.
attitudes and outcomes.
So, it's like um
I think one of the most fundamental
things really that everybody should be
clear about with themselves it's um
uh why why do I meditate? Like what what
is the purpose? What is the outcome I'm
hoping for
to
um
as a result of of my meditation. So,
whatever whatever the meditation is
doesn't matter we don't have to get into
that now here.
The rights and wrongs we they have
plenty of talks that um they deal with
those things.
Um but it's more like just uh
whatever notion of meditation that you
have um
like what is the reason behind it?
So, is that something um you're clear
about? Is that something that you
you you clearly see kind of the path
outlined required the outcomes of it?
Um and uh where where are those
motivations rooted in? So, what what do
you hope to achieve?
Cuz I think very often
uh you know people read the sutras
um
get the sense um contemporary Buddhism
various teachers instructions find
meditation techniques and so on and it's
helpful. Um so, it it does kind of um
Um so, it it does kind of um
uh always go hand in hand with these
Buddhist um instructions that are found
in the sutras you know they talk about
freedom and so on.
Uh freedom from suffering freedom from
desire freedom from hindrances um
but um I think um more often than not um
if you think about it today like on
today's terms
just that notion of freedom it's quite
ambiguous uh cuz people haven't really you know
uh cuz people haven't really you know
sat and and and philosophically really
get to the bottom of it. What does it
mean to be free for example?
So, it's just freedom it's you know
feels like this I have some notions but
more often than not it's it's um
it's simply misrepresented misconceived
and um confused.
So, um I think practically speaking if
you would take a sample of of your like
average average meditators and so on
I think more people would be confusing
just the notion of um peace whatever
whatever has
um
whatever has kind of uh enabled me to
get some sense of peace they would
confuse that for freedom. They would
think oh that's the freedom that the
Buddha was talking about in the sutras.
So, so that's therefore when I sit to
meditate free from distractions free
from things that disturb me in a in a
controlled environment I am peaceful.
And that uh that equals freedom or
that's bringing me closer to freedom.
But again as I said before so many times
if you actually
uh look at the sutras correctly as a as
a as a whole body of instruction as a as
a the the broadest context of
instruction um that's that the Buddha
gave to people
yeah the peace is uh is kind of the
result of freedom not other way around.
So, you might have peaceful experiences
here and there but uh if you're
confusing peace with freedom means you
would be
more often than not confusing a mere uh
agreeable uh circumstances comfort
with things uh up to your liking or
within your control you would confuse
that for the path of freedom and that
that couldn't be further from the truth.
So, it's kind of what happens basically
when such confusion exists uh when such
misrepresentation misrepresentation
exists in people
they would uh be merely um
pretty much going around hunting refined
pleasures refined peacefulness
um and um at the pretext of of freedom
freedom from suffering and so on and
other things that the sutras talk about
but in reality just kind of
creating this this mask of an underlying
agitation. So,
by equating the peaceful state we could
put it that way I guess by equating the
peaceful state you kind of end up still
acting out of the the the same cravings
that were
disturbing your peace like in any other
scenario. So, in other words your your your
So, in other words your your your
pursuit of the peaceful state become
like a like a
a subtle indulgence in a in a in a very
much in like a in a central domain in
the form of central craving.
So, it's not like a coarsely going after
the desires but the same motivation that
you have when you desire sense objects
or when you desire tactile wheel will
now the same desire to be peaceful
that's confused for freedom or whatever
that's basically that desire is still
the central desire.
And even if you invest like years and
years of effort in in like building this
this um elaborate environment and system that
um elaborate environment and system that
supports the practice of peace that
supports the non-disturbance that
supports pretty much uh all the circumstances
pretty much uh all the circumstances
that might be involved in it. Uh
if that original motivation and that
desire is never questioned
towards towards peaceful states as
valuable it's never questioned never
never reflected upon uh it's the whole
thing will still be a projection within
the central domain. It will be still
rooted in central craving.
So, that's why
more often than not people would today
would train rightly if they were
enduring the friction of the present
moment of the things that are kind of
pressuring you disturbing you then
just going blindly or at face value
following peaceful states.
And even if you do get peaceful states
you put them in a bracket so to speak.
You step back and you don't lose
perspective in regard to that.
So, that's why it's like it all of this
um as I often keep saying can can be
um
realigned correctly and and rekindled
through through right questioning.
So, you find meditation helpful you find
you find meditation helpful you find
sitting peacefully helpful.
That's fine but you got to not take that
for granted and also try and understand
it. So,
but not I don't mean understand peace
why peace is peaceful but understand why
is it that what you want.
So, why do you think the practice is
about um
being peaceful for example?
So, again it's not like a I need to find
the right answer the wrong answer. It's
more like I need to find the answer that
pertains to my motivation. Like why do I
want this? So, what do I think freedom
is? What do I think meditation is? What
do I think practice is?
So, when I dutifully
uh keep the precepts and sit to meditate
or go to a retreat and stuff
what exactly am I hoping to achieve? Do
I see that path of achievement clearly
outlined as in like oh if I do this I
clearly understand the results of it?
Or is it all based on kind of a vague
notion of well something good will
happen out of this some good will come
out of this.
And in the meantime I prefer it cuz uh I
feel peaceful and comfortable. I think
more often than not that's another
thing. >> [snorts]
>> [snorts]
>> See, if people confused peace for
freedom as in any peace they can get by any
as in any peace they can get by any
means necessary for freedom
uh they will inevitably
uh fall into a trap of pretty much uh
needing and preferring
comfort and confusing that for the
practice. So,
when I live in the environment when
there are no disturbances
when there are no
um
physical endeavors cuz usually like most
of the even like most of the monasteries
and stuff become that.
Many of the places become like very kind
of
um uh precious and padded around the
environment so so people become more and
more and more and more sheltered and
that practically is out just living in a
constant uh in in a comfort that you
couldn't have pretty much afforded even
as a layperson.
You know like comfort to to when I say
comfort I don't mean like the
like luxurious beds and stuff like that.
Sure, that can easily be
um
done with but it's more like
it's quite a privilege to be able to to
to live in the environment where
uh
there are no sight sounds smell taste
touches bombarding you.
So, but do you take that
uh within the right context or do you
take that for granted and just start to
depend now on the environment when there
are no provocations?
The environment that's comfortable cuz
you don't have to deal with anything cuz
nothing comes up cuz there's nothing
disturbing you.
So, it's not a problem to seek a
suitable peaceful environment.
But, if you're doing it for the wrong
reasons, it will lead to nowhere anyway.
So, the point is like
like are you afraid, for example, are
you afraid of being disturbed by the
external circumstances? Like, would that
uh undermine your meditation?
Would that would that um threaten it?
Then, that's not the meditation you
should be cultivating.
Because, again,
the whole samadhi,
the principle behind what the suttas
often talk about, it's like
immovability, imperturbability,
in face of sights that want to move you,
smells that want to move you, touches,
and so on.
So, yes, physical withdrawal
necessary in order to support the
precepts, but the work still needs to be done
but the work still needs to be done
towards the actual freedom of an
imperturbability, and not fall into a trap of oh, I've
and not fall into a trap of oh, I've
withdrawn myself from sensuality.
Now, I live in a controlled environment
when there are more
most of the time there are no
distraction no no bombardments of
sensuality, no disturbances,
no physical work, no labor, no not
really having to to endure sight,
sounds, um smell, taste, touches, heat,
cold, all these things the suttas talk
about. And then, people would kind of
fall into that sort of
trap of
being completely dependent on that very
artificial environment,
and taking for granted and even
confusing it for peace.
Because, there's nothing disturbing me
here, therefore I'm not disturbed,
therefore for me there is no work to do.
Even if obviously internally
people know that there is plenty of work
to do.
So, that's why it's like
you want to start questioning your
motivation way before you become
that dependent on these artificial
circumstances that it because again,
you're depending on comfort, you're
depending on sense of control, and
that's not going to be easy to undo.
So, when you sit to meditate, or you sit and
when you sit to meditate, or you sit and
contemplate,
another thing you could be asking
yourself, am I truly actually seeking liberation
am I truly actually seeking liberation
that the Buddha was talking about?
Like, is is that what I am aiming at?
>> [snorts]
>> Or, am I just deep down really just want
a slightly better way to hide from
suffering when it comes,
a slightly stronger lid to keep on top
of it, slightly better way to manage.
Um so, it's like what do I want,
basically? That's pretty much what you
should be asking yourself. Like, when
I'm doing these practice, when I'm doing
when I'm practicing the dhamma, when I'm
studying the suttas, when I'm
meditating, when I'm contemplating,
what do I want from it? What is my goal?
Like, how how far do I want to go?
Do I even have a have I thought about
it? >> [snorts]
>> Because, as I said,
if these motivations are never revealed,
they will be aligned with
um pretty much the place where you come
from. And the place you come from, it's
going always going to be in the
beginning the place of desire, the place
of sensuality.
So, the more you do your practices of
the dhamma, whatever you think those
are, without
um unraveling and revealing these as I
said, the context of your motivation as
to why you're doing it in the first
place, what's your tacit kind of
assumptions and implications,
uh then everything you do in the
in the name of practice, your
meditation, the precept, everything,
it's just going to become basically a
an extension, like a like a subtle
uh
continuation of the subtle addiction to
to the sense of control,
to comfort, to the preferences, to uh
avoiding pain, prolonging pleasure.
So, it it just becomes
very much the extension of the same
thing. It doesn't really uproot
anything. So, that's why again,
So, that's why again,
through the questioning, you would
reveal this motivation. Then, when when
your intentions behind why you're
meditating, why you're doing this become
somewhat clear, well, new questions will
will will arise, or new questions will
present themselves.
So, am I seeking peace
am I seeking peace
um
with a view that such peace and freedom
will come on a kind of full
understanding, say,
of suffering, of feelings, of craving,
fully training my mind out of the
desire? Or, do I deep down still carry an
Or, do I deep down still carry an
assumption that
that peace will just sort of be bestowed
upon me
if I do these random things rightly
long enough, I will have a breakthrough,
which is kind of a form of like a like
an instant gratification of of what
you've been working for, like a reward.
Oh, well, I I'm doing this, I'm doing
this, I don't see the connection, I
don't see the the the the clear like
there's no clear understanding, as I
said, of the outcomes, and so on.
But, I'm just doing it cuz it makes some
sense, I learned about it, and I'm
waiting for the peace, for liberation,
for whatever you want to call it, to
happen to me.
So, that's the difference between like
are you actually developing it as
something that can be understood how to
be developed, or you're just doing
random stuff, and then hoping that
development which just going to come
your way? So,
So,
so, that's like um
and in the yeah, say if you say if you
ask these questions as a part of your
meditation, um and contemplation,
you might get different answers
different times.
Like, sometimes your motivation might be
leaning one way, sometimes might be the
other way, sometimes old views might
creep in. That's why again, maintaining
the clarity of that context,
uh and and broadening it in that sense
with a further clarification is is
something that you can't have too much
of. As the as the sutta said, like you can't
As the as the sutta said, like you can't
have too much of sati, basically.
>> [snorts]
>> Um and then uh see, all of these other
subtle and tacit little views that you
might have here and there are going to
start floating up to the surface.
So, it's like another see, you start
questioning yourself, oh, why am I
meditating?
Am I really,
you know, seeking freedom from suffering
the way the suttas outline it?
Or, you know,
I just want to feel basically peaceful
and undisturbed undisturbed here and
now, but I'm not really willing to to to give
but I'm not really willing to to to give
up too many things.
Um
that already shows you like what
direction your mind is leaning, what
direction the animal is preferring.
Uh and then, you can already contrast
that with the instruction that the
Buddha gave, and see well, is that is
that aligned with what the Buddha said?
Is that aligned with
you know, countless of statements of
saying sensuality is an obstruction,
um sensual desires are are peril,
they're in the way, acting out of ill
will is is unwholesome, it's ignoble,
and stuff.
So, you could already then see whether
you are trying to practice dhamma on
your own terms, or you're actually
trying to align it with how it's how
it's presented in the suttas. Cuz then,
that kind of leads to a natural natural
question like, okay, so
how about
if I practice the dhamma, or say, how
about I'm seeking? Like, it's fine to
want to be peaceful, and it's fine to
want to be happy. There's no problem
with that.
It's just how you go about it.
Are you just uh acting to are you just
sort of um investing your efforts that
are still very much driven and rooted by
the same sensual desire that you're
completely refusing to question,
um emotional preferences, or are you
willing to go against those if needed?
So, then the question you should be
asking you could be asking yourself if
you want. I mean, you don't have to do
any of this.
But, if you want, it's like
could I
even imagine, say, being happy, being
content, uh being peaceful even, yeah,
uh being peaceful even, yeah,
without needing to do anything on
account of anything that happens to me? So,
is that a possibility for me? Like, is
that a possibility for my mind?
If it's not, can I imagine it? Can I
imagine the benefits of it? Would would
that be a beneficial skill to develop?
Like, genuinely.
Doesn't matter what comes your way,
doesn't matter what happens to you,
doesn't matter who says what, what you
experience, whether you lose or you
gain, or
>> [sighs]
>> um whatever worldly wind blows blows
your way,
uh
could you remain
peaceful without needing to deal with
anything that comes your way, without
needing to move,
without needing to do anything, without
needing to act out,
without needing to manage, without
needing to counter,
could you remain untouched pretty much?
Um
Can you imagine how that would feel?
Would that be a valuable thing, as I
said, would it be a valuable thing to
develop?
Then, you can ask yourself, okay, so
how would one go about developing that?
How would I do it? Like, if somebody
were to ask you,
hey, how how how would you develop that?
What comes to your mind as an answer?
Like, how is it that you understand
the the imperturbability,
um, immovability, contentment, peace,
being above the suffering like the lotus
is above the water and the mud that it
grew out of and stuff like that. All the
all the stuff the suttas talk about.
Like, can you wrap your head around it
without like, as I said, just resorting
to like a an answer, a line from the
suttas or something? Like, no, you're
doing this as a contemplation, as a
reflection. When you sit quietly
as a part of your meditation, you
actually want to be uncovering and
revealing these very sort of
views that you carry, inclinations,
leanings, preferences, cuz that is how
sati is developed. That's how sati is
broadened. That's how sati becomes,
uh, the context becomes more
established. Um, so, yeah, so like, can I be
untouched? Can I be Or, say even if I
can't be untouched, I can't imagine how
it would feel to be untouched by
unpleasant things and so on.
Can I remain immovable? Cuz see, you
might not have a choice whether you're
touched or not, but you certainly have a
choice whether you're going to act out
of it or not.
So, do you see? Do you recognize?
do you see? Do you recognize?
Can you discern the threshold? The
extent of
how far you could go, how far you could
take on without needing to,
you know, act out of panic or pressure
or hindrance.
Like, where is that line?
where is that line?
Is it as soon as something unpleasant
touches you, your mind spirals out of
control and you're just acting out of
all of these habits, firing on all
cylinders just to cover it up, just to
manage, just to regain the sense of
pleasure and control and comfort
and get rid of the pain? Or are you able
to stay with it?
So, are you able to stay with the
discomfort? Are you able to stay with
with like a
mental threats,
um, that your your mind can be showing
you, uh, throwing at you?
Um,
and where's the line? How how how far
you can stay with it?
Cuz again, it's like these things need
to be like, you need to shine the light
onto them
through these reflections and questions
cuz otherwise, they will remain like
hidden as a guiding principle behind your,
as a guiding principle behind your,
uh, efforts, investments, and everything
else. Cuz you're not looking at them, they're
Cuz you're not looking at them, they're
there in the background influencing
through preferences, through leanings,
through these subtle cravings.
And that's a point, like you don't
uncover the subtle cravings through like
psychologizing about mechanics of
cravings and results and stuff. You
uncover them by questioning your own
motivation. Cuz craving is always where your desire
Cuz craving is always where your desire
is.
Where your where your intention is to do
this, to do that.
So, by questioning that,
unraveling, clearing out anything that's
sort of covering it up,
it's, you know, you can eventually reach
a point where where where things are
clearly understood on the level that
they are, so that when you're touched by
pleasure, touched by pain,
um, there is enough of width, so to speak,
there is enough of width, so to speak,
in your mind
that it wouldn't fall into the trap of
immediate reaction, immediate movement,
immediate activation. So, see like say
something touches you unpleasantly and
then you immediately have the habitual
thoughts. Say some somebody said
something upsetting.
And you immediately have the habitual
thoughts. They would be just And then
obviously you'll be speaking, saying
stuff, doing stuff, acting out of it.
Say that's a somebody who's not
restrained. But, if you have been practicing,
But, if you have been practicing,
training rightly, restraining,
reflecting as I said, and and and and
delving deeper and deeper, broader and
broader into these contexts and
preconceived notions,
you you will find yourself in a position
of
something says so somebody says
something upsetting to you, the upset is
felt. And even the thoughts might start
And even the thoughts might start
rushing out, but you remain still.
And it's like, oh,
oh, look, all these floods came up, but
I was I was I was not taken by them.
And that obviously
is going to give you more confidence.
Oh, so can I develop this principle even
further? Whereby there will be no even
floods coming. The only reason the
floods were coming is cuz I was still
liable to be kind of taken by them. Now,
when I've sufficiently remained and
practiced immovability on the level of
body, speech, and mind,
the floods dry up basically. Cuz there's
there I'm not there anymore basically to
be taken by those those those those
those same torrents and so on.
So, yeah, so that's that can be a meditation
yeah, so that's that can be a meditation
certainly
for some period of time because as I said,
some period of time because as I said,
plenty more questions
will come up if you start asking these
things rightly and not immediately
jumping in and for an answer as I said,
but asking them and then staying in that
mode of a question asked
without defaulting to an answer that's
going to satisfy and plug the hole, so
to speak. No, no, no. Ask a question and
leave it there for a while. Don't ignore
it. Don't start thinking about something
else. And see what the question points at.
And see what the question points at.
And that's how you start start getting
the answers that are more and more
aligned with how things actually are, with the
with how things actually are, with the
principles of the five aggregates and
everything else that the Buddha talked
about.